Guide to the Dawn Langley Simmons Papers, 1848-2014 RL.01190
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dawn Langley Simmons papers
1848-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Simmons, Dawn Langley
RL.01190
20.0 Linear Feet
Dawn Langley Simmons (1937-2000), was a British author. She started her career editing newspaper society columns and went on to become a prolific biographer and the author of Man Into Women: A Transsexual Autobiography (1971). The Dawn Langley Simmons Papers span the years 1848-2001, with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1969 and 2001. The collection houses extensive files of correspondence dating from the 1950s to 2000, with topics ranging from Simmons' formative years in Great Britain, her relationship with her mother, Marjorie Hall Copper, literary circles in Great Britain, later personal events such as her wedding, and Simmons' development as a writer. Significant correspondents or individuals mentioned in letters include Margaret Rutherford, Isabel Whitney, Vita Sackville-West, Sir Harold Nicolson, Nigel Nicolson, Robert Holmes, and Edwin Peacock. The collection also includes writings by Simmons in the form of typescripts and diaries; printed material and clippings, including articles and reviews by and about Simmons; legal and financial papers; an extensive collection of scrapbooks; photographs; audiovisual materials; and other material relating to Simmons' personal life and career as a writer.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Dawn Langley Simmons Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1966-2005.
Biographical Note
Chronology
probably 1922 Born to Jack Copper and Marjorie Hall Ticehurst; later adopted as an adult by the actress Margaret Rutherford
1946 Emigrated to Canada, to Ojibway Reservation, Lake Nipigon, Canada; served as missionary, teacher, and midwife
1947-1949 Returned to England, taught theater and art at the Gregg School, Croydon
1950-1952 Returned to the U.S., worked as a society editor for The Nevada Daily Mail, Missouri
1952 Moved to New York, became society columnist for the Port Chester Daily Item
1955 Published Me Papoose Sitter
1957 Hall's play, Saraband for a Saint, performed in Harlem, New York
1957 Published Princess Margaret: An Informal Biography
1962 Hall moved permanently to Charleston Hall legally adopted by Margaret Rutherford and her husband
1963 Publication of Vinnie Ream: The Story of the Girl Who Sculpted Lincoln
1967 Gender affirmation surgery, Johns Hopkins University, with name changed to Dawn Pepita Langley-Hall.
1963 Publication of Jacqueline Kennedy, a Biography
1969 Jan. Married John-Paul Simmons in Charleston, first legal interracial marriage in South Carolina; second wedding ceremony performed in England
1970 Publication of Rose for Mrs. Lincoln: A Biography of Mary Todd Lincoln
1971 Natasha Simmons born; birth certificate, created at a later date, declares Dawn Langley Simmons the birth mother
1982 Divorced John-Paul Simmons
1983 Published biography, Margaret Rutherford: Blithe Spirit
1995 Published autobiography, Dawn: A Charleston Legend
2000 Sept. 18 Died, Charleston, S.C.
Collection Overview
The Dawn Langley Simmons Papers span the years 1848-2001, with the bulk of the papers being dated between 1969 and 2001. The collection consists of material collected and created by Simmons when she was using the names Gordon Langley Hall, Dawn Pepita Langley Hall, and Dawn Langley Simmons. Extensive files of correspondence dating from the 1950s to 2000 document Simmons' formative years in Kent and Sussex, Great Britain; her relationship with her mother, Marjorie Hall Copper; literary circles in Great Britain; later personal events such as her wedding and purchase of her house in Charleston, S.C.; and Simmons' development as a writer. Significant correspondents or individuals mentioned in letters and other materials include Robert Holmes, Sir Harold Nicolson, Nigel Nicolson, Edwin Peacock, Margaret Rutherford, Vita Sackville-West, and Isabel Whitney. The collection also includes writings by Simmons in the form of typescripts and diaries; printed material and clippings including articles by and about Simmons; legal and financial papers; an extensive collection of scrapbooks; photographs; audiovisual materials; and other material relating to Simmons' personal life and career as a writer. The writings in the collection are primarily typescripts but include a few proofs and printers' galleys. Many of the pieces are unpublished. The publication process of the 1995 autobiography Dawn: A Charleston Legend is extensively documented by a series of edited manuscripts and proofs as well as correspondence with the publisher. Collection materials also document to some extent sex change treatments begun in 1967 at the Gender Identity Clinic of Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore; Simmons' 1969 interracial marriage to John-Paul Simmons; and the disruption in their lives in part brought on by the negative reaction of Charleston society to their marriage.
The collection also contains an electronic file of an unpublished manuscript, WANTING MAGIC, by J. Theodore Ellis, including his unpublished notes, footnotes, and reflections based on the works of Hall-Simmons and related individuals, as well as professional studies of transsexualism and sexual identity. Includes a printout of selected pages of the manuscript. There is also Ellis' copy of Simmon's GREAT WHITE OWL OF SISSINGHURST.
The Audiovisual Materials Series includes video and audio tape recordings and photographs. The recordings include professionally-produced audio broadcasts discussing Simmons' transgender life and her interracial marriage - and an amateur audio tape of Simmons' wedding. Several hundred photographs document Isabel Whitney and her family as well as Simmons' family and friends. Original recordings are closed to research; listening copies are available for most items. Otherwise, staff must arrange for use copies to be made.
The largest series in the collection, the Correspondence Series consists chiefly of incoming correspondence, spanning five decades, from family and friends, from publishers concerning Simmons' writing, and from other individuals. There is some correspondence written by Simmons scattered throughout.
Brief but detailed entries in the eleven volumes housed in the Diaries Series describe Simmons' writing career, emotional states, and family matters during the time periods from 1975-1976 and 1987-1989, ending with the years 1990-1994.
The Legal and Financial Papers Series chiefly consist of documents concerning Simmons' father, Jack Copper, Isabel Whitney and her family and estate, Simmons and her husband, and Simmons' inheritance from Whitney.
The Printed Materials Series houses clippings, travel guides, flyers, and other items that document Simmons' interests, travels, and hobbies; includes early journalistic writings (chiefly columns), and a hardcover copy of her children's book, the Great White Owl of Sissinghurst.
The twenty-odd albums found in the Scrapbooks Series feature memorabilia, clippings, photos, and correspondence assembled by Simmons concerning her writing career, family, hobbies, and interest in celebrities and royalty.
The small Volumes Series consists of two manuscripts collected by Simmons: a nineteenth-century diary written by Sarah Combs, a transcript of this diary, and an early twentieth century travelogue written by a member of the Whitney family.
The Writings Series primarily consists of typescripts of works by Simmons. There are a few written pieces by other authors. Other writings by Simmons can be found in the Correspondence Series (in the topical correspondence folders for the 1950s and 1960s and scattered throughout in other files); in the William Carter Spann Series, which contains research Simmons conducted in preparation for a book on President Carter's nephew; in the Diaries Series; and in the Printed Materials Series, which contains early columns and later writings by Simmons.
Oversize Materials housed separately from the main collection include posters, cover proofs, newspaper and magazine clippings, and a few diplomas and awards.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Related Material
Isabel Whitney Papers, Dawn Langley Simmons, and Two Lives of Baby Doe Collection (manuscript)
Elmer L. Andersen Library, University of Minnesota.
Sound recordings; Photographs; Authors, American -- Biography; Video recordings; Scrapbooks; Sex change -- United States; Transgender people -- United States; Authors, American -- Southern States; Mothers and sons -- Great Britain; Women authors, American -- Biography; Women authors, American -- Southern States; Transsexuals -- South Carolina -- Charleston; Interracial marriage -- South Carolina -- Charleston; Diaries; Charleston (S.C.) -- Social life and customs; Kent (England) -- Social life and customs; Whitney, Isabel Lydia; Peacock, Edwin, 1910-1989; Simmons, Dawn Langley; Sackville-West, V. (Victoria), 1892-1962; Rutherford, Margaret, 1892-1972; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Nicolson, Nigel; Nicolson, Harold George, Sir, 1886-1968; Holmes, Robert; Copper, Marjorie Hall Ticehurst; Combs, Sarah
- Correspondence Series, 1874-2000 and undated, 24 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of personal and business correspondence received and written by Gordon Hall/Dawn Langley Hall Simmons. The early correspondence consists of letters from Simmons' mother, Marjorie Hall (Ticehurst) Copper, describing her work on the household staff of Sir Harold Nicolson and his wife, Victoria Mary Sackville-West, Lady Nicolson, in Cranbrook, Kent, England. The letters concern family news and local gossip, Lady Nicolson's death, the family affairs and writings of Nigel Nicolson, and Marjorie Copper's views of events in the United States. Later correspondence is from Simmons' friends and acquaintances. Folders of topical correspondence house letters written by Simmons to Edwin Peacock and Robert Holmes, and a few of Peacock's replies; correspondence received by Isabel Whitney, and material concerning the settlement of her estate; and Simmons' correspondence with the publisher Wyrick and Co. detailing the publication process of Dawn: A Charleston Legend, and containing older material Simmons sent to the publisher. Other folders in the topical correspondence sub-grouping house early correspondence and clippings from Isabel Whitney and Gordon Hall to Emmeline Paige, editor at the Villager, and materials that Hall gathered on Helen Invicta Hall, Natasha Simmons, and Isabel Whitney. Smaller amounts of correspondence are found in the Scrapbooks Series. Correspondence arranged in chronological order by date.
  - 1952 May-1968 Dec., 10 folders (Box 1)
  - 1969 Jan.-1972 Apr., 10 folders (Box 2)
  - 1972 May-1972 Sept., 6 folders (Box 3)
  - 1972 Oct.-1973 July, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - 1973 Aug.-1974 Feb., 7 folders (Box 5)
  - 1974 Mar.-1974 Sept., 7 folders (Box 6)
  - 1974 Oct.-1975 Mar., 8 folders (Box 7)
  - 1975 Apr.-1975 Oct., 7 folders (Box 8)
  - 1975 Nov.-1976 April, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - 1976 May-1976 Nov., 7 folders (Box 10)
  - 1976 Dec.-1977 July, 8 folders (Box 11)
  - 1977 Aug.-1978 May, 10 folders (Box 12)
  - 1978 June-1979 Feb., 9 folders (Box 13)
  - 1979 Mar.-1980 Oct., 8 folders (Box 14)
  - 1980 Nov.-1981 June, 7 folders (Box 15)
  - 1981 July-1981 Oct., 5 folders (Box 16)
  - 1981 Nov.-1983, 7 folders (Box 17)
  - 1985 Apr.-1987 Jan., 8 folders (Box 18)
  - 1987 Feb.-1987 July, 8 folders (Box 19)
  - 1987 May-1989 Dec., 8 folders (Box 20)
  - 1994 Apr.-1999 Mar. and undated, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - 1999 Apr.-2000 Aug. and undated, 4 folders (Box 22)
  - Topical correspondence, 1874-1999 and undated (bulk 1956-1999)
    - James Williams material, 1982-1994 (Box 23)
    - Correspondence with publishers, 1978-1999 (Box 23)
    - Correspondence with Edwin Peacock, 1971-1989 (Box 23)
    - Correspondence with Robert Holmes, 1970-1977 and undated (Box 23)
    - Isabel Whitney materials, 1874-1963 (Box 23)
    - Clippings and Natasha Simmons juvenilia, 1980s-1990s and undated (Box 23)
    - Correspondence with Wyrick and Co. Publishers, 1989-1999 and undated, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Correspondence, printed material, and photographs gathered by Hall and related to Isabel Whitney's last years, the NYC apartment, and 56 Society Street in Charleston, 1963-1968 and undated, 1 folder (Box 24)
    - Gordon Hall to Emmeline Paige, Villager editor, 1956-1962, 1971 and undated, 1 folder (Box 24)
    - Biographical and genealogical materials about Helen Invicta Hall, 1931-1967 and undated, 1 folder (Box 24)
    - Letters from Isabel Whitney to Emmeline Paige, 1930s and undated, 1 folder (Box 24)
- Diaries Series, 1975-1976, 1987-1989, 1990-1994, 1 box
  Consists of eleven volumes, one for each year with the exception of 1991, kept intermittently by Simmons. Brief but detailed entries refer to daily weather, activities, emotional states, conversations and correspondence, family matters, and personal upheavals or milestones. Portions of some volumes remain unused.
  - Diaries (Box 25)
- Legal and Financial Papers Series, 1848-1990s and undated, 5 folders
  Consists of documents concerning Simmons, her father Jack Copper, Isabel Whitney, and the Whitney family. The Jack Copper material includes papers issued by the United Kingdom government, such as a passport and driver's license, and some memorabilia. The Whitney family material consists of genealogical papers and the will of Martha H. Whitney, Isabel Whitney's mother. The financial papers are made up of various receipts and invoices concerning Dawn Simmons, her husband John-Paul Simmons, and Vita Sackville-West's purchase of a Ford sedan in 1959. The legal papers include publishers' contracts with Gordon Langley Hall, documents concerning the inheritance from Isabel Whitney and the purchase of 56 Society Street in Charleston, S.C. The legal material also includes paperwork on Whitney family cemetery plots. Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
  - Legal and financial papers (Box 26)
- Printed Materials Series, 1911-1993 and undated, 5 boxes
  Files of miscellaneous materials including publisher's proofs of two of Dawn Simmon's books; hardcover edition of The Great White Owl of Sissinghurst as well as J. Theodore Ellis' copy of the book; a bible once belonging to Isabel Whitney with handwritten notes; early journalistic writings under the identity of Gordon Hall (chiefly columns); newspaper clippings; travel and gallery brochures; church publications; magazines; catalogues; and advertisements. Contains material on the British royal family, and the actresses Bette Davis and Charlotte Cushman. Other printed material is included in the Wyrick and Co. folder in the Correspondence Series. Most of the series is grouped alphabetically by subject. Most newspaper clippings are arranged chronologically by year. Some items are listed in the Oversize Materials series at the end of this finding aid.
  - Printed materials (Box 27-31)
- Scrapbooks Series, 1946-1989, 29 boxes
  Consists of more than twenty scrapbooks assembled by Gordon Hall/Dawn Simmons over the course of several decades. The album pages feature clippings about movie stars and British royalty, articles written by Gordon Hall and Marjorie Hall, advertisements and promotional material for several of Hall's books, some correspondence, and photographs of Isabel Whitney's funeral and Sissinghurst Castle. Arranged in rough chronological order. Other photographs can be found in the Audiovisual Materials Series.
  - Bette Davis clippings, 1947-1950 (Box 32)
  - Bette Davis clippings, 1951-1952 and undated (Box 33)
  - Bette Davis clippings, 1952-1953 and undated (Box 34)
  - Bette Davis, clippings, 1953-1962 and undated (Box 35)
  - Gordon Langley Hall, clippings, 1952-1953 (Box 36)
  - Gordon Langley Hall, clippings and correspondence, 1958-1968 (Box 37)
  - Gordon Langley Hall, clippings and correspondence, 1962-1963, Bette Davis clippings, 1989 (Box 38)
  - Gordon Langley Hall, clippings of writings on British royalty, 1955-1957 and undated (Box 39)
  - Gordon Langley Hall, correspondence, 1960 (Box 40)
  - Gordon Langley Hall and Marjorie Hall, clippings, 1955-1957 (Box 41)
  - Isabel Whitney funeral photographs, 1962 (Box 42)
  - Joan Crawford, clippings, 1953-1959 (Box 43)
  - London Illustrated News souvenir edition, Coronation of Edward VII, 1902 (Box 44)
  - [Princess] Margaret, clippings, 1958 and undated (Box 45)
  - Marjorie Hall, writings, 1956-1957and undated (Box 46)
  - Me Papoose Sitter, promotional material and memorabilia, 1956-1958 (Box 47)
  - Me Papoose Sitter, promotional material and memorabilia, 1956-1961 (Box 48)
  - Newspaper notices and announcements, 1946-1948 (Box 49)
  - Peter Jumping Horse at the Stampede, promotional material, 1962 (Box 50)
  - Sissinghurst Castle photographs and postcards album, undated (Box 51)
  - Vinnie Ream, promotional material and correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box 52)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 69-71)
  - Scrapbook, 1958-1961 (Box 72)
  - Scrapbook, Princess Margaret (Box 73)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1964 (Box 74)
  - Scrapbook, Romantic Times (Box 75)
  - Photograph album (Box 75)
  - Photograph albums (2) (Box 76)
  - Marjorie Hall Scrapbook (Box 77)
  - Scrapbook (Box 77)
  - Gordan Hall Scrapbook (Box 78)
- Volumes Series, 1878-1880, 1909-1911 and undated, 1 box
  Two small manuscript volumes collected by Hall: a nineteenth-century diary written by Sarah Combs, a transcript of this diary, and an early twentieth century travelogue written by a member of the Whitney family.
  - Volumes (Box 53)
- William Carter Spann Materials Series, 1969-1981 and undated, 1 box
  Consists of material collected by Simmons on William Carter Spann, President Jimmy Carter's nephew. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Drafts of writings on William C. Spann by Dawn L. Simmons, 1977 and undated (Box 54)
  - Prison authority evaluations, 1969-1978 (Box 54)
  - William C. Spann-Dawn L. Simmons correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 54)
  - William C. Spann personal correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 54)
  - Clippings, 1976-1978 (Box 54)
- Writings Series, 1945-1995, 2012-2014 and undated, bulk 1969-1990s, 12 boxes
  Folders house drafts and manuscripts of Simmons' writings, and a few pieces by others. Arranged in alphabetical order. Cover proofs of Dawn: A Charleston Legend have been removed to oversize housing.
  Contains an electronic file of an unpublished manuscript, WANTING MAGIC, by J. Theodore Ellis, dated 2012-2014, including his unpublished notes, footnotes, and reflections based on the works of Hall-Simmons and related individuals, as well as professional studies of transsexualism and sexual identity. There is a printout of selected pages of the manuscript.
  Some typescripts have the typed name "Gordon Langley Hall" crossed out in pen and replaced with "Dawn Langley Simmons."
  - The Ballad of Dawn and John-Paul, undated (Box 55)
  - The Ballad of Dawn and John-Paul, manuscript with handwritten notes, 1969 (Box 55)
  - The Boy in Washington Square, undated (Box 55)
  - The Boy in Washington Square, typescript, 1973 (Box 79)
  - Camilla the Husky Who was Lost in Charleston, 1995 (Box 55)
  - Children of the Moor, undated (Box 55)
  - Draft of article on Isabel Whitney's paintings of Brooklyn Heights, undated (Box 55)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, first draft, 1991 (Box 55)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, manuscript, 1991 (Box 55)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, manuscript, undated (Box 56)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, editorial materials and computer disc, undated (Box 56)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, dust jacket design, undated (Box 56)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, editorial material, undated (Box 56)
  - Photographic materials collected for publication in Dawn: A Charleston Legend, undated (Box 56)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, edited manuscript, 1992 (Box 57)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, galley proof, 1995 Jan. 17 (Box 57)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, manuscript, 1995 Feb. 2 (Box 57)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, edited manuscript, undated (Box 57)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, manuscripts, undated, 4 folders (Box 58)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, typescript, undated (Box 58)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, blueprint printing and empty boards, undated (Box 59)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend, galley proofs, 1995 Feb., 5 folders (Box 59)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend clippings, book reviews and publicity, 1990s, folder 1 of 2 (Box 59)
  - Dawn: A Charleston Legend clippings, book reviews and publicity, 1990s, folder 2 of 2 (Box 60)
  - Deserted Wife, undated (Box 60)
  - An English Grandmother, undated (Box 60)
  - The Girl Who Sculpted Lincoln (2 drafts), undated (Box 60)
  - The Great White Owl of Sissinghurst (3 drafts), 1992-1993 and undated (Box 60)
  - The Green Orchid: A Novel, undated (Box 60)
  - Gulielma, undated (Box 60)
  - Harriet Tubman article, manuscript, 1980 (Box 60)
  - History of Sussex (?), undated (Box 60)
  - I Was a Papoose Sitter, undated, 2 folders (Box 61)
  - Me Papoose Sitter, play version, undated (Box 61)
  - Lady Bird and Her Daughters, article draft, 1967 (Box 61)
  - Lady Marjorie: The Diary of a Catskill Cat, undated (Box 61)
  - Loon Bay People, manuscript, 1980 (Box 61)
  - Madness Haunts Actress's Daughter, article draft, undated (Box 61)
  - Margaret Rutherford: A Blithe Spirit, 1980, 2 folders (Box 61)
  - Margaret Rutherford's Cookbook and Other Family Secrets, undated (Box 62)
  - The Mark of Caroline, undated (Box 62)
  - The Mark of Caroline, typescript (Box 79)
  - Mother Rutherford, first draft, 1979 (Box 62)
  - Mrs. John-Paul: A Love Story, 1974 (Box 62)
  - My Tiara For a Pig, undated (Box 62)
  - Porty's Motel, undated (Box 62)
  - Porty's Motel, typescript, 1973 (Box 79)
  - The President's Nephew: An American Tragedy, outline and notes, undated (Box 62)
  - A Princess Recaptures New York, undated (Box 62)
  - A Princess Recaptures New York, typescript, 1973 (Box 79)
  - Romeo Was a Lady: A Biography of Charlotte Cushman, manuscript, undated, 2 folders (Box 63)
  - Romeo Was a Lady, undated (Box 63)
  - Romeo was a Lady, typescript (Box 79)
  - Rosalynn Carter: The Woman Behind the Man, 1978 (Box 63)
  - A Rose for Mrs. Lincoln, galley, 1969 (Box 63)
  - The Sawdust Tail, typescript of corrections, 1963 (Box 63)
  - Sleep On, Dear Randall, undated (Box 63)
  - Sleep On, Dear Randall, photocopy, undated (Box 64)
  - Sleep on, Dear Randle, typescript, 1973 (Box 79)
  - Song of the Wilderness, undated (Box 64)
  - Tapestry of the Rose: A Play in Five Acts, manuscript, undated (Box 64)
  - Though Our Tombs Be Dark, manuscript, undated (Box 64)
  - The Twelve Holy Nights (2 drafts), undated (Box 64)
  - Twelve Holy Nights, typescript, 1973 (Box 79)
  - A Very Little Miracle in Harlem, manuscript, undated (Box 64)
  - Vita's Country, manuscript (foreword and chapter one), undated (Box 64)
  - Vita's Country, manuscript photocopy, undated (Box 64)
  - Who Killed Aunt Fay?, manuscript, undated (Box 65)
  - Yankee Alias Romeo, manuscript, undated (Box 65)
  - Notes and drafts, undated, 3 folders (Box 65)
  - Writings by Others, 1945-1959, 2008-2014 and undated (Box 65)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, circa 1910-1980s and undated, bulk 1979-1980s, 4 boxes